<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<!--
  NOTE:  This XML file is input used to produce the authoritative copy of an
  OpenID Foundation specification.  The authoritative copy is the HTML output.
  This XML source file is not authoritative.  The statement ipr="none" is
  present only to satisfy the document compilation tool and is not indicative
  of the IPR status of this specification.  The IPR for this specification is
  described in the "Notices" section.  This is a public OpenID Foundation
  document and not a private document, as the private="..." declaration could
  be taken to indicate.
-->
<rfc category="std" docName="openid-connect-backchannel-1_0" ipr="none">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="5" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc private="Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="OpenID Connect Back-Channel Logout 1.0">OpenID Connect
    Back-Channel Logout 1.0 - draft 03</title>

    <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
	<uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
      <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ve7jtb@ve7jtb.com</email>
	<uri>http://www.thread-safe.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="23" month="August" year="2016" />

    <workgroup>OpenID Connect Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>OpenID Connect 1.0 is a simple identity layer on top of the OAuth 2.0
      protocol. It enables Clients to verify the identity of the End-User based
      on the authentication performed by an Authorization Server, as well as to
      obtain basic profile information about the End-User in an interoperable and
      REST-like manner.</t>

      <t>
	This specification defines a logout mechanism that uses direct back-channel
	communication between the OP and RPs being logged out;
	this differs from front-channel logout mechanisms,
	which communicate logout requests from the OP to RPs via the User Agent.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">

      <t>
	OpenID Connect 1.0 is a simple identity layer on top of the OAuth 2.0
	<xref target="RFC6749"/>
	protocol. It enables Clients to verify the identity of the End-User based
	on the authentication performed by an Authorization Server, as well as to
	obtain basic profile information about the End-User in an interoperable and 
	REST-like manner.
      </t>
      <t>
	This specification defines a logout mechanism that uses direct back-channel
	communication between the OP and RPs being logged out;
	this differs from front-channel logout mechanisms,
	which communicate logout requests from the OP to RPs via the User Agent.
      </t>
      <t>
	An upside of back-channel communication is that it can be more reliable
	than communication through the User Agent, since in the front-channel,
	the RP's browser session must be active for the communication to succeed.
	(If the RP's browser tab was subsequently used to navigate to an unrelated page,
	the RP session will be active unless the user uses the back button to return to it.)
	Both the <xref target="OpenID.Session">OpenID Connect Session Management 1.0</xref>
	and <xref target="OpenID.FrontChannel">OpenID Connect Front-Channel Logout 1.0</xref>
	specifications use front-channel communication,
	which communicate logout requests from the OP to RPs via the User Agent.
      </t>
      <t>
	A downside of back-channel communication is that the session state maintained between
	the OP and RP over the front-channel, such as cookies and HTML5 local storage,
	are not available when using back-channel communication.
	As a result, all needed state must be explicitly communicated between the parties.
	Furthermore, RPs must implement an application-specific method of terminating
	RP sessions with the OP upon receiving back-channel logout requests;
	this can be more complicated than simply clearing cookies and HTML5 local storage state,
	which is often all that has to happen to implement logout in response to
	front-channel logout requests.
      </t>
      <t>
	Another significant limitation of back-channel logout is that the RP's
	back-channel logout URI must be reachable from all the OPs used.
	This means, for instance, that the RP cannot be behind a firewall or NAT
	when used with public OPs.
      </t>
      <t>
	This specification can be used separately from or in combination with
	OpenID Connect Session Management 1.0 and/or
	OpenID Connect Front-Channel Logout 1.0.
      </t>

      <section anchor="rnc" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

	<t>
	  In the .txt version of this specification,
	  values are quoted to indicate that they are to be taken literally.
	  When using these values in protocol messages,
	  the quotes MUST NOT be used as part of the value.
	  In the HTML version of this specification,
	  values to be taken literally are indicated by
	  the use of <spanx style="verb">this fixed-width font</spanx>.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>
	  This specification uses the terms 
	  "Authorization Server",
	  "Client", "Client Identifier", and "Redirection URI"
	  defined by <xref target="RFC6749">OAuth 2.0</xref>,
	  the term "User Agent" defined by <xref target="RFC7230">RFC 7230</xref>,
	  the terms "Session" and "Session ID" defined by
	  <xref target="OpenID.FrontChannel">OpenID Connect Front-Channel Logout 1.0</xref>
	  and the terms defined by
	  <xref target="OpenID.Core">OpenID Connect Core 1.0</xref>
	  and <xref target="JWT">JSON Web Token (JWT)</xref>.
	</t>
	<t>
	  This specification also defines the following term:
	  <list style="hanging">
      
            <t hangText="Logout Token">
	      <vspace/>
              <xref target="JWT">JSON Web Token (JWT)</xref> similar to an ID Token
	      that contains Claims about the logout action being requested.
            </t>

	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Backchannel" title="Back-Channel Logout">
      <section anchor="BCSupport" title="Indicating OP Support for Back-Channel Logout">
	<t>
	  If the OpenID Provider supports
	  <xref target="OpenID.Discovery">OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</xref>,
	  it uses this metadata value to advertise its support for back-channel logout:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="backchannel_logout_supported">
	      <vspace/>
	      OPTIONAL.
	      Boolean value specifying whether the OP supports back-channel logout,
	      with <spanx style="verb">true</spanx> indicating support.
	      If omitted, the default value is <spanx style="verb">false</spanx>.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  It SHOULD also register this related metadata value:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="backchannel_logout_session_supported">
	      <vspace/>
	      OPTIONAL.
	      Boolean value specifying whether the OP can pass
	      a <spanx style="verb">sid</spanx> (session ID)
	      Claim in the Logout Token to identify the RP session with the OP.
	      If supported, the <spanx style="verb">sid</spanx>
	      Claim is also included in ID Tokens issued by the OP.
	      If omitted, the default value is <spanx style="verb">false</spanx>.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="BCRegistration" title="Indicating RP Support for Back-Channel Logout">
	<t>
	  Relying Parties supporting back-channel-based logout register a back-channel logout URI
	  with the OP as part of their client registration.
	  The domain, port, and scheme of this URL MUST be the same as that of
	  a registered Redirection URI value.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The back-channel logout URI MUST be an absolute URI as defined by
	  Section 4.3 of <xref target='RFC3986' />.
	  The back-channel logout URI MAY include an
	  <spanx style='verb'>application/x-www-form-urlencoded</spanx> formatted
	  query component, per Section 3.4 of <xref target='RFC3986' />,
	  which MUST be retained when adding additional query parameters.
	  The back-channel logout URI MUST NOT include a fragment component.
	</t>
	<t>
	  If the RP supports
	  <xref target="OpenID.Registration">OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration 1.0</xref>,
	  it uses this metadata value to register the back-channel logout URI:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="backchannel_logout_uri">
	      <vspace/>
	      OPTIONAL.
	      RP URL that will cause the RP to log itself out
	      when sent a Logout Token by the OP.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  It SHOULD also register this related metadata value:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="backchannel_logout_session_required">
	      <vspace/>
	      OPTIONAL.
	      Boolean value specifying whether the RP requires that
	      a <spanx style="verb">sid</spanx> (session ID)
	      Claim be included in the Logout Token to identify the RP session with the OP
	      when the <spanx style="verb">backchannel_logout_uri</spanx> is used.
	      If omitted, the default value is <spanx style="verb">false</spanx>.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Tracking" title="Remembering Logged-In RPs">
	<t>
	  OPs supporting back-channel logout need to keep track of
	  the set of logged-in RPs so that they know what RPs to contact
	  at their back-channel logout URIs to cause them to log out.
	  Some OPs track this state using a "visited sites" cookie.
	  OPs are encouraged to send logout requests to them in parallel.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="LogoutToken" title="Logout Token">
	<t>
	  OPs send a JWT similar to an ID Token to RPs called a Logout Token
	  to request that they log out.
	  ID Tokens are defined in Section 2 of <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The following Claims are used within the Logout Token:
	</t>

	<t>
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="iss">
	      <vspace/>
	      REQUIRED.
	      Issuer Identifier, as specified in Section 2 of <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
	    </t>

	    <t hangText="sub">
	      <vspace/>
	      REQUIRED.
	      Subject Identifier, as specified in Section 2 of <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
	    </t>

	    <t hangText="aud">
	      <vspace/>
	      REQUIRED.
	      Audience(s), as specified in Section 2 of <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
	    </t>

	    <t hangText="iat">
	      <vspace/>
	      REQUIRED.
	      Issued at time, as specified in Section 2 of <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
	    </t>

	    <t hangText="jti">
	      <vspace/>
	      REQUIRED.
	      Unique identifier for the token, as specified in Section 9 of <xref target="OpenID.Core"/>.
	    </t>

	    <t hangText="events">
	      <vspace/>
	      REQUIRED.
	      Claim whose value is an array of strings,
	      the first of which is
	      <spanx style="verb">http://schemas.openid.net/event/backchannel-logout</spanx>.
	      This declares that the JWT is a Logout Token.
	    </t>

	    <t hangText="sid">
	      <vspace/>
	      OPTIONAL.
	      Session ID - String identifier for a Session.
	      This represents a Session of a User Agent or device
	      for a logged-in End-User at an RP.
	      Different <spanx style="verb">sid</spanx> values are used to identify
	      distinct sessions at an OP.
	      The <spanx style="verb">sid</spanx> value need only be unique
	      in the context of a particular issuer.
	      Its contents are opaque to the RP.
	      Its syntax is the same as an OAuth 2.0 Client Identifier.
	    </t>

	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  The following Claim MUST NOT be used within the Logout Token:
	</t>
	<t>
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="nonce">
	      <vspace/>
	      PROHIBITED.
	      A <spanx style="verb">nonce</spanx> Claim MUST NOT be present.
	      Its use is prohibited to make a Logout Token syntactically invalid
	      if used in a forged Authentication Response in place of an ID Token.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Logout Tokens MAY contain other Claims.
	  Any Claims used that are not understood MUST be ignored.
	</t>
	<t>
	  A Logout Token MUST be signed and MAY also be encrypted.
	  The same keys are used to sign and encrypt Logout Tokens
	  as are used for ID Tokens.
	  NOTE: The Logout Token is compatible with
	  <xref target="I-D.hunt-idevent-token">Security Event Token (SET)</xref> draft -03.
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <preamble>
	    A non-normative example JWT Claims Set for a Logout Token follows:
	  </preamble>
	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  {
   "iss": "https://server.example.com",
   "sub": "248289761001",
   "aud": "s6BhdRkqt3",
   "iat": 1471566154,
   "jti": "bWJq",
   "sid": "08a5019c-17e1-4977-8f42-65a12843ea02",
   "events": [ "http://schemas.openid.net/event/backchannel-logout" ]
  }
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="BCRequest" title="Back-Channel Logout Request">
	<t>
	  The OP uses an HTTP POST to the registered back-channel logout URI
	  to trigger the logout actions by the RP.  The POST body uses the
	  <spanx style="verb">application/x-www-form-urlencoded</spanx> encoding
	  and must include a <spanx style="verb">logout_token</spanx> parameter
	  containing a Logout Token from the OP for the RP identifying the
	  End-User to be logged out.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The POST body MAY contain other values in addition to
	  <spanx style="verb">logout_token</spanx>.
	  Values that are not understood by the implementation MUST be ignored.
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <preamble>
	    The following is a non-normative example of such a logout request
	    (with most of the Logout Token contents omitted for brevity):
	  </preamble>

	  <artwork><![CDATA[
  POST /backchannel_logout HTTP/1.1
  Host: rp.example.org
  Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

  logout_token=eyJhbGci ... .eyJpc3Mi ... .T3BlbklE ...
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Validation" title="Logout Token Validation">
	<t>
	   Upon receiving a logout request at the back-channel logout URI,
	   the RP MUST validate the Logout Token as follows:
	</t>

	<t>
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>
	      If the Logout Token is encrypted, decrypt it using the
	      keys and algorithms that the Client specified during Registration
	      that the OP was to use to encrypt ID Tokens.
	      If ID Token encryption was negotiated with the OP at Registration time
	      and the Logout Token is not encrypted, the RP SHOULD reject it.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Validate the Logout Token signature in the same way that
	      an ID Token signature is validated.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Validate the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx>,
	      <spanx style="verb">aud</spanx>,
	      and <spanx style="verb">iat</spanx>
	      Claims in the same way they are validated in ID Tokens.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Verify that the Logout Token contains an
	      <spanx style="verb">events</spanx> Claim
	      whose value is an array of strings,
	      the first of which is
	      <spanx style="verb">http://schemas.openid.net/event/backchannel-logout</spanx>.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Verify that the Logout Token does not contain a
	      <spanx style="verb">nonce</spanx> Claim.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Optionally verify that another Logout Token with the same
	      <spanx style="verb">jti</spanx> value has not been recently received.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  If any of the validation steps fails, reject the Logout Token
	  and return an HTTP 400 Bad Request error.
	  Otherwise, proceed to perform the logout actions.
	</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="BCActions" title="Back-Channel Logout Actions">
	<t>
	  After receiving a valid Logout Token,
	  the RP locates the session identified by the
	  <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> and
	  <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx> Claims
	  and optionally the <spanx style="verb">sid</spanx> Claim.
	  The RP then clears any state associated with the identified session.
	  The mechanism by which the RP achieves this is implementation specific.
	  If the identified End-User is already logged out at the RP when the logout request
	  is received, the logout is considered to have succeeded.
	</t>
	<t>
	  In the case that the RP is also an OP serving as an identity provider
	  to downstream logged-in sessions, it is desirable for the logout request
	  to the RP to likewise trigger downstream logout requests.
	  This is achieved by having the RP/OP send logout requests to its downstream RPs
	  as part of its logout actions.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="BCResponse" title="Back-Channel Logout Response">
	<t>
	  If the logout succeeded, the RP MUST respond with HTTP 200 OK.
	  If the logout request was invalid, the RP MUST respond with HTTP 400 Bad Request.
	  If the logout failed, the RP MUST respond with 501 Not Implemented.
	  If the local logout succeeded but some downstream logouts have failed,
	  the RP MUST respond with HTTP 504 Gateway Timeout.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The RP's response SHOULD include <spanx style="verb">Cache-Control</spanx>
	  directives keeping the response from being cached to prevent cached responses
	  from interfering with future logout requests.
	  It is RECOMMENDED that these directives be used:
	</t>
	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  Cache-Control: no-cache, no-store
  Pragma: no-cache
]]></artwork></figure>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="RPInitiated" title="RP-Initiated Logout Functionality">
      <t>
	This specification incorporates the RP-initiated logout functionality
	specified in Section 5 of <xref target="OpenID.Session">OpenID Connect Session Management 1.0</xref>
	by reference.
	All the same metadata values and messages are used by the RP to request that
	the OP log out RPs and then possibly redirect back to the initiating RP
	as are used in that specification.
	Therefore, they are not repeated here.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	The signed Logout Token is required in the logout request to prevent
	denial of service attacks by enabling the RP to verify that
	the logout request is coming from a legitimate party.
      </t>
      <t>
	The kinds of Relying Parties that can be logged out by different implementations
	will vary.  Implementations should make it clear, for instance,
	whether they are capable of logging out native applications or only Web RPs.
      </t>
      <t>
	OPs are encouraged to use short expiration times in Logout Tokens,
	preferably at most two minutes in the future,
	to prevent captured Logout Tokens from being replayable.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <section anchor="DynRegRegistration" title="OAuth Dynamic Client Registration Metadata Registration">
	<t>
	  This specification registers the following client metadata definitions
	  in the IANA "OAuth Dynamic Client Registration Metadata" registry
	  <xref target="IANA.OAuth.Parameters"/>
	  established by <xref target="RFC7591"/>:
	</t>

	<section anchor="DynRegContents" title="Registry Contents">
	  <t> <?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>
		Client Metadata Name: <spanx style="verb">backchannel_logout_uri</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Client Metadata Description:
		RP URL that will cause the RP to log itself out
		when sent a Logout Token by the OP
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Change Controller: OpenID Foundation Artifact Binding Working Group - openid-specs-ab@lists.openid.net
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Specification Document(s): <xref target="BCRegistration"/> of this specification
	      </t>
	    </list>
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>
		Client Metadata Name: <spanx style="verb">backchannel_logout_session_required</spanx>
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Client Metadata Description:
		Boolean value specifying whether the RP requires that
		a <spanx style="verb">sid</spanx> (session ID)
		Claim be included in the Logout Token to identify the RP session with the OP
		when the <spanx style="verb">backchannel_logout_uri</spanx> is used
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Change Controller: OpenID Foundation Artifact Binding Working Group - openid-specs-ab@lists.openid.net
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Specification Document(s): <xref target="BCRegistration"/> of this specification
	      </t>
	    </list>
	  </t>
	</section>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
      </section>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230"?>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Core" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Core 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute, Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B." surname="de Medeiros">
            <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>
          </author>

	  <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
	    <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce</organization>
	  </author>

          <date day="8" month="November" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Discovery" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-discovery-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute, Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Edmund Jay" initials="E." surname="Jay">
            <organization abbrev="Illumila">Illumila</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="8" month="November" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Registration" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-registration-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute, Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="8" month="November" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.FrontChannel" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-frontchannel-1_0.html">
	<front>
	  <title>OpenID Connect Front-Channel Logout 1.0</title>

	  <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
	    <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
	  </author>

	  <date day="23" month="August" year="2016" />
	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Session" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-session-1_0.html">
	<front>
	  <title>OpenID Connect Session Management 1.0</title>

	  <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
	    <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute, Ltd.</organization>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
	    <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
	    <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B." surname="de Medeiros">
	    <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
	    <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce</organization>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="Edmund Jay" initials="E." surname="Jay">
	    <organization abbrev="Illumila">Illumila</organization>
	  </author>

	  <date day="23" month="August" year="2016" />
	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="JWT" target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7519'>
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Token (JWT)</title>

	  <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
	    <organization>Microsoft</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
	      <uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
	    </address>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
	    <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>ve7jtb@ve7jtb.com</email>
	      <uri>http://www.thread-safe.com/</uri>
	    </address>
	  </author>

	  <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
	    <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute</organization>
	    <address>
	      <email>n-sakimura@nri.co.jp</email>
	      <uri>http://nat.sakimura.org/</uri>
	    </address>
	  </author>

	  <date month="May" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7519" />
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7519"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IANA.JWT.Claims" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/jwt">
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Token Claims</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
	  <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IANA.OAuth.Parameters" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/oauth-parameters">
        <front>
          <title>OAuth Parameters</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
	  <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7591"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-hunt-idevent-token-03.xml" ?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
	The OpenID Community would like to thank the following people for
	their contributions to this specification:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>John Bradley (ve7jtb@ve7jtb.com), Ping Identity</t>
	  <t>Brian Campbell (bcampbell@pingidentity.com), Ping Identity</t>
	  <t>Pedro Felix (pmhsfelix@gmail.com), individual</t>
          <t>Michael B. Jones (mbj@microsoft.com), Microsoft</t>
	  <t>Todd Lainhart (lainhart@us.ibm.com), IBM</t>
	  <t>Nat Sakimura (n-sakimura@nri.co.jp), Nomura Research Institute, Ltd.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Notices" title="Notices">
      <t>Copyright (c) 2016 The OpenID Foundation.</t>

      <t>The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) grants to any Contributor, developer,
      implementer, or other interested party a non-exclusive, royalty free,
      worldwide copyright license to reproduce, prepare derivative works from,
      distribute, perform and display, this Implementers Draft or Final
      Specification solely for the purposes of (i) developing specifications,
      and (ii) implementing Implementers Drafts and Final Specifications based
      on such documents, provided that attribution be made to the OIDF as the
      source of the material, but that such attribution does not indicate an
      endorsement by the OIDF.</t>

      <t>The technology described in this specification was made available
      from contributions from various sources, including members of the OpenID
      Foundation and others. Although the OpenID Foundation has taken steps to
      help ensure that the technology is available for distribution, it takes
      no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual property
      or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation
      or use of the technology described in this specification or the extent
      to which any license under such rights might or might not be available;
      neither does it represent that it has made any independent effort to
      identify any such rights. The OpenID Foundation and the contributors to
      this specification make no (and hereby expressly disclaim any)
      warranties (express, implied, or otherwise), including implied
      warranties of merchantability, non-infringement, fitness for a
      particular purpose, or title, related to this specification, and the
      entire risk as to implementing this specification is assumed by the
      implementer. The OpenID Intellectual Property Rights policy requires
      contributors to offer a patent promise not to assert certain patent
      claims against other contributors and against implementers. The OpenID
      Foundation invites any interested party to bring to its attention any
      copyrights, patents, patent applications, or other proprietary rights
      that may cover technology that may be required to practice this
      specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="History" title="Document History">
      <t>[[ To be removed from the final specification ]]</t>

      <t>
	-03
	<list style="symbols">
          <t>
	    Changed from using a <spanx style="verb">logout_only</spanx> claim
	    to using a logout event in the Logout Token.
	    The Logout Token is compatible with
	    <xref target="I-D.hunt-idevent-token">Security Event Token (SET)</xref> draft -03.
	  </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
	-02
	<list style="symbols">
          <t>
	    Renamed HTTP-Based Logout to Front-Channel Logout.
	  </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
	-01
	<list style="symbols">
          <t>
	    Cleaned up some text left over from the HTTP-Based Logout spec.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    Clarified the conditions under which HTTP 504 Gateway Timeout is returned.
	  </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
	-00
	<list style="symbols">
          <t>
	    Wrote the initial version based on working group discussions.
	    The structure of this specification is intentionally similar
	    to the OpenID Connect HTTP-Based Logout 1.0 specification.
	  </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
